hi there and so in the first video I
identified three things that I was going
to focus on in these videos namely rival
ristmas the broadcast modality of
decision making and the complex versus
complicated
the reason it's those three things the
reason those those are the three
subjects of these videos are that in
every iteration of game a it is some
combination of those three dynamics
which have eventually caused the
collapse of the civilization and so it
is those three areas in particular that
game B is focused on trying to find a
way to overturn these dynamics so that
the civilization is long-term
sustainable you know not just for a
couple of hundred years but you know
over many millennia and continues to
evolve and continues to grow so that's
the that's the vision for game B so this
video is focused on the rival risk and
the anti rivalries and just before I get
into definitions I would like to offer a
warning that it is sometimes the case I
will try to give these warnings whenever
this happens that the language that is
used is not used in the everyday sense
of the word and so rival wrists nurse is
not the same thing as rivalry so rivalry
in the sense of you know two squash
players getting together evenly matched
have a really really hard game one wins
one loses but actually in a broader
sense both people at one they've had a
really good time they've played better
than they've ever played before you know
so they both both are winners in that in
that grander sense in a similar way if
you're having an argument with someone
in order to refine and strengthen the
proposition that they're offering you
know it's noisy again it's a
collaborative effort you're arguing it's
it's it's you know you're you're
exhibiting rivalry but it is not rival
risk because you're not seeking to beat
the other person right you're not
seeking to win at their expense and this
is the crucial difference between
rivalry which can be constructive and
even generative and rival risk which is
win
you know one person gains at the other
person's expense it's a it's a crucial
difference to understand okay so that
said let's move on and look at
definitions of the rival risk and the
non rival risk as I am using them in
this video so the domain of the rivalry
spaces recovers any kind of physical
item right where I have it somebody else
can't have it and and and so that win
lose dynamic is perpetuated so anything
at all food water even air
I mean air is a good example is at the
moment air is basically clean right we
just breathe it it's completely abundant
so we don't compete for it right there's
no rival risk dynamics surrounding air
if however in the future the air gets
yucky and smelly and we can't breathe it
anymore then clean air will become a
rival risk commodity right some people
will have it and some people won't and
the people that have it have it at the
expense of the people that don't have it
so you know even things which are
completely non rival risk that's the
that's the end of the spectrum where you
have complete abundance so there's no
need to compete for it even things which
are non rivals can become rivals and
vice versa things which are highly rival
risk by being made more available can
become less rival s so that's that's
pretty straightforward the anti rival
risk domain and these are things which
there's a couple of strands to this so
the first thing is that the more people
have it it does not become depleted in
any way right so this applies to
non-physical things good examples of non
rival risk things are what ideas broadly
in general but more specific examples
the Internet is an excellent example
mathematics is an excellent example
languages are an excellent example
Facebook is a really good example so
within all of these things the more
people that use them the better they are
right the more powerful they are the
more useful they are and it doesn't cost
the people that already have it it costs
them nothing for more people to have it
right so that's that's one thing it does
not get depleted it gets stronger as
more people use it and the other thing
is that it's generative right so anti
rivalries things allow
all things to come on top of them again
the Internet is an excellent example
right so once the internet was invented
then a whole bunch of new technologies
were possible as a consequence of the
invention of the internet and then once
those were layered on top and that
prepared the ground for another layer of
innovation to come on top of that and so
on and so on and so on and so just to
sum up one more time the anti rival risk
is not depleted the more people but have
it in fact it's more useful stronger
better the more people that have it and
is generative allows new innovation to
be built on top of the old innovation
okay so now that the definitions are out
of the way it's worth making the point
that we have existed in rival risk
dynamics for every iteration of game a
for 12,000 years because for the very
large majority that there was genuine
scarcity and so to have a mindset of I
need to protect this because otherwise
someone else can take it and then I
don't have it and there's not enough to
go around you know that that kind of
mindset was largely justified but that
is no longer the case right the world we
live in now the technology available to
us now scarcity in a huge number of
physical items could be simply
alleviated right and therefore reducing
the degree to which we need to be rival
Burress over these things
the ultimate evolution of rivalries
dynamics is war and this is why it's
such a crucial thing to tackle because
as I said in the first video our ability
to do war now is such that we could wipe
us entirely out and not to mention a
great deal of the rest of the stuff on
the planet so the need to tackle
rivalries dynamics is crucial the other
really ugly part of this is because we
have this rival risk mindset right this
is the lens through which we see the
world we evaluate everything in these
terms even things which are
fundamentally anti rivals get dragged
into the rival risk domain so using
Facebook again as an example right I
mean Facebook is a fundamentally anti
rival risk thing the more people that
have it them more useful it becomes its
generative all sorts of groups and idea
tanks and so on start forming within the
context of that right so it is it is
absolutely an anti rivalries thing
however because it exists in a rival
risk environment it is forced to
generate revenue for itself how does it
do that through advertising what gets
more advertising revenue well more time
on site was sticky you are the more time
you can get people to spend on your site
the bigger advertising revenues will be
and so Facebook is strongly incentivized
to use whatever means it can to attract
people to excite
and to keep them there right is there
they're essentially competing for your
attention they're competing with you for
your attention and for your time and so
you are now in a rival risk relationship
with Facebook because this is unlikely
to be in your best interest writer to
spend hours and hours a day on Facebook
as they would like you to so you are now
in rival risk relationship with a
fundamentally anti rival hrus thing and
so if we go back to the definition of
the anti rival is that it is generative
by trapping it in the rival risk
environment you are restricting its
ability to be generative the concept of
intellectual property patent laws these
things serve to restrict the number of
people who can work on any given idea
and so the generative nature of the anti
rivalries is forever stifled and stymied
by its existence in a fundamentally
rivalries environment and this to me is
the most important aspect of the game be
ideal of transmuting the rival risk into
the anti rivalry signing apart from the
avoidance of war which is I've already
mentioned is crucial because you know
our ability to make war is so
self-destructive now but you know if you
can picture for a moment a global
completely anti rival replying field
right where every single contribution
that everybody makes every innovation
every new idea that anybody has is
accessible to everyone right it's a it's
the property of the commons collectively
owned by everyone and so I make my
contributions in the good faith
knowledge and understanding that
everybody else is making their
contributions and we all have access to
all contributions via the common pool
and so this is the anti ultimate anti
rival risk environment because this you
know the the generative nature of the
ability to build on everybody's
contributions at any given moment would
just mean that the rate of progress
would be would be staggering ok so just
a summer the rivalries dynamics that
have always existed in game a have torn
civilizations apart in the past you know
rivalries and rivalries leads to things
like corruption
defection and hoarding and so on which
is hugely detrimental to the society as
a whole and so tackling rival risk
dynamics is one of the key features of
the game be project and this broadly
happens in two ways number one
alleviating scarcity so that things
which have the potential to be rival as
are made as non rival risk as possible
and the second part of it more
importantly it might you is unshackling
the anti rival risk from the restrictive
environment of the rival bus so I think
that pretty much covers it next one is
going to be on broadcast modality versus
decentralized since making networks and
they kind of link together because you
know this problem of rival richness has
never been solved before so the creation
of new sense making and decision-making
networks may have the possibility of
solving that which has not been solved
before so I look forward to seeing you
next time thank you very much for
watching